A Guide to the Prince Edward County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1754-1913
Library of Virginia
- 1838-015, Royall Watkins, etc. vs. Owen H. Tucker.
  Estate Dispute. This case includes information about a slave auction and estate accounts documenting expenses for keeping enslaved people and hiring them out.
- 1839-002, John Thackston vs. Hudson Wilson.
  Contract Dispute. The case contains a contract for construction of the Prince Edward courthouse and a bill for construction of a brick house.
- 1841-008 - Daniel Mitchell and wife, etc. vs. Atrix of John Pearson, etc.
  Estate Dispute. The case includes a letter from a widow in Danville asking help to prevent the sale of the slave Clem.
- 1841-057, John Brown vs. Hampton Giles.
  Estate Dispute. The case involves a dispute over a tract of land given to Brown's father when he was emancipated by Richard Randolph.
- 1842-020, William M. Carter vs. Dabney Cosby.
  The defendant is an artisan from Milton, North Carolina, who was contracted to build a Presbyterian Church in Prince Edward County. The case includes a letter to Cosby about the debt, and a letter from Cosby explaining he didn't have employment in Prince Edward, so he went to Milton where there was plenty of work.
- 1843-010, Edward Wooldridge vs. Thomas A. Legrand, Administrator.
  Estate Dispute. The case contains a list of the 44 grandchildren of Simon (?) Wooldridge and a detailed genealogy, including the children of Ralph Wooldridge, Jonah Wooldridge, Nancy Baugh, formerly Wooldridge; Robert, Wooldridge, Polly Inge, Edward Wooldridge; and Rhoda Scruggs, formerly Wooldridge, as well as some of the grandchildren's marriages. The accounts contain yearly wages paid for work as overseer.
- 1843-012, Zackariah Goodman vs. Trustees of Appomattox Co.
  The case involves a proposal to construct locks to improve navigation on the Appomattox River.
- 1843-015, Jesse Bradley vs. Thomas H. Anderson.
  Estate Dispute. The case contains an agreement between Lucy Anderson and Thomas Anderson to allow Lucy to move west with her dower slaves.
- 1844-022, Thomas Doswell vs. Executor of William Doswell, etc.
  Estate Dispute. The case contains multiple combined suits documenting migration to Madison County, Alabama, and Christian County, Kentucky. It contains several letters from Madison County, Alabama territory, 1818-1820, and from Lawrence County (state?).
- 1844-044, Nathaniel Penick vs. Samuel W Venable, etc.
  Contract Dispute. The case involves a dispute over division of a Presbyterian Church in Cumberland County, in Hanover Presbytery.
- 1845-014, Trustee of John Clarke, etc. vs. Alexander Scott, Assignee
  Estate Dispute. The valuation of slaves in this case document slave marriages and families.
- 1845-016, John James Ewing vs. Executors of James Ewing.
  Contract Dispute. This case documents the money spent per slave on corn and the amount of corn grown by slaves for themselves on a plantation in 1819. It also documents expenses paid for a midwife.
- 1846-011, Nicholas C. Read vs. Samuel W. Venable
  Business Dissolution. This case involves a dispute between former business partners. It documents their tobacco business which involved the buying, selling, and manufacturing of tobacco.
- 1847-004, Richard Gallion and wife vs. Robert Bowman.
  Debt. This case documents Saluda Gallion's work as a school teacher in Prince Edward County before she was married, and her efforts to collect claims from families.
- 1847-005, John Walthall vs. Milton and Quarles.
  Contract Dispute. This case involves the right to use Page's patent for a portable circular sawmill and includes a copy of the patent.
- 1847-011, Fanny Bowman vs. Executor of Philip Bowman.
  Estate Dispute. This case pertains to the estate of Philip Bowman, a free African American man who was married to an enslaved woman owned by the Venable family. When Philip Bowman died, his mother sued to acquire property he had tried to leave to his wife, who was still enslaved. The Venable family tried to protect the widow's interests by promising to care for her, but later put her in the poor house to live out her days there.
- 1847-015, John N. Brooks vs. Samuel P. Rice, etc.
  This case documents the treatment of Samuel P. Rice, president of Hampden Sydney College, with leeches, and the hiring of slaves from Rice by the Trustees of Hampden Sydney College for the year 1845.
- 1847-024, Henry Jackson by etc. vs. John H Smith, etc.
  Estate Dispute. The defendant is described as a slave trader, buying up slaves "to be carried to the South." The plaintiff alleges his inheritance in slaves is unjustly being sold and carried South.
- 1848-002, Committee of Josiah Chambers vs. Administrator of James Madison, etc.
  Estate Dispute. This case involves James Madison's embezzlement of funds from Josiah Chambers' estate, and the fraudulent selling of lots in the town of Farmville. This case includes testimony about the legitimacy of the marriage of Chambers, who was declared mentally unsound by the court; about the sale of slaves for profit by Chamber's Committee, and the provision of seasonal clothing for Chambers. It also contains receipts of medical care for slaves.
- 1848-031, Reuben A. Rudd, etc. vs. Reuben H. Dejarnett, Trust., etc.
  Estate Dispute. This large case pertains to a marital separation, an accusation of insanity for wanting to ruin the family by selling all the slaves; a plea to avoid the sale of a young child away from his mother "from a humane motive," the sale of certain slaves to acquire money to buy a plantation for the trustees; accusations of fraud. The records include accounts for hiring out and selling slaves to administer a trust.
- 1850-015, Frances Anderson by etc. vs. R.C. Anderson.
  Estate Dispute. The case contains a will, written in St. Augustine, Florida and proved in Chesterfield County in 1847, describing two slaves who "have been raised in a factory in Richmond, and would be of little value in the country."
- 1852-011, John J Flournoy vs. Thomas W Epes.
  Contract Dispute. This case concerns a contract to keep the Eagle Hotel in Farmville. The records include accounts that document furnishings of the hotel, such as plates, glasses, mustard, pillow cases, towels, etc.
- 1852-015, Devisees of Archer Allen, etc. vs. Nancy Allen, etc.
  Estate Dispute. This case involves conveyance in 1804 of a property called Gold Mine in Buckingham County, wherein there "was a mine of gold ore, or other valuable metals."
- 1852-016, John H. Leigh and wife, etc., vs. Executor of Daniel Allen.
  Estate Dispute. This case includes accounts listing the prices of tobacco sold at Randolph's warehouse in Farmville from 1831-1840.
- 1853-006, Edward Williams vs. John Stevens, etc.
  Estate Dispute. This suit involves the plaintiff's efforts to regain a slave family, a mulatto woman and her children, who "plaintiff was unwilling for particular reasons to part." Plaintiff claims slaves were sold to a creditor at half their market value, on the provision that plaintiff could regain the slaves when he repaid the purchase price. When his daughter loaned him the money, the defendant claimed no such agreement had been made, and informed her he had already sold the slaves. The case includes a deposition taken at a store house owned by McNaught and Ormand in Newport, Wakulla County, Florida.
- 1853-010 - William Borum and wife, etc. vs. Executor of David Ellington.
  Estate Dispute. In this case, the heirs of David Ellington seek unsuccessfully to revoke Ellington's bequest to two emancipated slaves.
- 1854-010, Trustee of James Madison vs. Thomas L. Morton, etc.
  Estate Dispute. This suit identifies several enslaved people who were carpenters; it also documents migration to Yazoo City, Mississippi, and Alabama and a Cumberland Presbyterian congregation.
- 1858-032, Joseph T. Redd, etc. vs. Admr. Of Thomas Read
  A letter dated 1858 is filed with the suit in which the guardian of Read's children expressed his desire that theslaves be sold, rather than divided, in the interest of the children.
- 1860-028, Guardian of Maria S. Dupuy, etc., vs. Maria S. Dupuy, etc.
  Estate Dispute. This case contains a petition to sell a slave, George, described as "disorderly, rebellious, and thievish," and one whose "influence tends to corrupt other slaves."
- 1867-020, Joseph D. Chambers, etc. vs. Administer of Josiah Chambers, etc.
  Estate Dispute. This case includes a list of slaves, their occupations, and to whom they were sold as part of the estate division (Images 462-464). In some instances, familial relationships are noted.
- 1867-045, Joel Elam vs Thomas G Lindsay and wife, etc.
  Will of Aaron Lindsay specifies slaves to be sold are not to be sold to a trafficker nor to anyone known to mistreat their slaves.
- 1872-034, Mahaly Johnson vs. Jacob Shepperson.
  Former slaves who were not married to each other; custody of child Cary at issue; depositions about character of each, whether or not Cary goes to school, general treatment of child. Shepperson's former owner testifies to his character.
- 1873-001, Dosha~, etc. vs. Executors of John Watson, etc.
  Estate dispute. This suit documents the emancipation and removal to Liberia of 66 enslaved people in 1857. The court record includes a list of people freed, with names, approximate ages, family relationships, and the number of deaths among them after reaching Liberia. The plaintiffs are suing the executors for distribution of funds intended for their use in Liberia.
- 1873-038, Agnes W. Watkins, Sr., etc. vs. Exr. of Henry E Watkins, etc.
  Slaves are listed in family groups with ages and relationships given.
- 1911-023, Samuel Jones vs. Susan Jones and Susan Jones vs. Samuel Jones
  Divorce suit. Susan Jones is being represented by an African American lawyer named Giles B. Jackson. The case contains some letterhead from Jackson's office noting that he is licensed to practice in front of the Virginia Supreme Court. Giles B. Jackson was a native of Goochland County, Virginia, born enslaved. After the Civil War, he worked as a laborer for the Stewart family, a prominent Richmond family. Subsequently, he was employed in the law offices of William H. Beveridge. Beveridge tutored Jackson, who went on to become the first black attorney to practice before the Supreme Court of Virginia. Jackson organized and promoted the Jamestown Negro Exhibit at the Jamestown Tercentennial in 1907. A year later, he published A History of the Negro Race of the United States.